Hot water for sale! Let's buy hot water.
Don't be greedy
Hot water for three kopeks.
Buy hot water!
Don't be stingy. Hot water for sale!
Hot water! Buy hot water!
Come here, young boy!
A Gift for Stalin
There is only the newly named Sabyr,
which means ''humble.''
Something unusual happened this morning.
A young goat was running in the streets
of a modern Jerusalem.
A pitiful sound of a lost baby goat
hindered the voices of Muedzinov
and bell sounds.
lt was asking to take him back
into the stable.
But who knows where it is.
The train full of people sent to the camps
and relocated to Kazakhstan in 1 949
was on the road
for almost two weeks. . .
Grandpa, l've brought water for you.
Hear, O lsrael,
the Lord our God is one Lord. . .
Grandpa.
Shma lsrael Adonai Alohaina Adonai Ahad
Barukh Shem Kvod Malkhuto Leolam Vaed.
Grandpa.
The boy did not know the words
of the prayer
but understood that before dying,
his grandpa,
an old Moscow tailor named Jacob Povzner,
was begging God for the boy. . .
One dies, take the other one.
Do you want me to arrange
the marriage for you?
We'll get a good woman for you!
Do you want a fat one or a skinny one?
l love fat ones.
You are a fool, Kasym, any of them
will go for you!
l would get married.
Do you want to get one from
the exiled settlers?
How about Verka from Algir?
Hey, Kasym, any one of them will
go for you, here-there
Here you are contused,
but there you are not.
Stop it. Let's go.
We are getting out.
Senior Lieutenant Zhusupov, Regional in
Charge of the Ministry of lnternal Affairs.
Do you have water, Lieutenant?
Yes, we do, Major.
Get in line, one by one.
We have counted, sir,
there are seven dead people,
sorry, dead ones.
Bury them.
Yes, Major! Not for the first time.
Get ready to unload.
Move, move! Go! Go!
Quickly! You are like a cow.
Stay together!
l said not to mingle with
other compartments.
Quickly, quickly, one by one!
Help him! Go quickly!
Get out one by one. Sit on the ground!
We are arranging the water distribution.
Regional in charge Balgabai,
commander of troop number one,
Faty Shyn Lo from the lnternational
Brigade of Comrade Kasym has arrived.
l'll break your legs, you dungan face.
Comrade major is a good specialist.
Gold hands.
All right, listen to me carefully.
The load is completed, seven pieces.
Drive away for twenty kilometers
and dig them there.
Do you understand?
What are you? What are you?
Who are you?
Railroad man, half military.
You have to answer in a military way.
ls he deaf?
Blind?
Comrade major, he is a bit contused.
Shit.
l was warned in Moscow about
all these Kazakh tricks!
Don't spill water, don't push.
You get it, go. lt's enough for everyone.
Rush, rush, quickly.
What are you looking at?
Start unloading.
Put bodies on the trolley.
Quickly, move!
Everyone, go to your compartment.
One by one.
What water?
Enough, there will be no water.
Loading. Quickly!
So, what, old man, is it stinking?
Do you, people,
want to get us into courts?
His name is Sashka, he is an orphan,
Kasym, Kasym, go to the boss,
go to the boss.
Alive! Alive! ln the name of God, Jesus.
lt's a human!
Go, go!
Hurry up! Move away from the doors.
Close the compartments.
So, what old man, let them go free!
Yes, sir!
By the car, one by one get in line. . .
lnto the cars.
Balgabai!
Balgabai, don't touch the child.
Hey, this one seems to be alive.
You, the dungan bastrad!
Forget forever who you are,
that is the only way to survive.
How much time has he been among
the dead bodies, smelling death?
He is alive, was put in the list
of the dead by a soldier.
Only his fear gave him a feeling of life.
Oh, Almighty, accept their innocent,
dead bodies,
and prepare a place for them in heaven.
Amen.
Faty, let's go.
l said: l love you. You said: so, what?
l said: only for you.
l will get all stars.
Here is tea.
What are we going to do, Kazak?
Listen, let's take him to the orphanage.
Here-there, while no one has seen him.
What are looking at me for?
lt's dangerous, do you understand?
Oh, no, l would not tell anyone.
You know me, Kasym.
l know, Faty. l know.
Hey, Kasym,
his soul is fighting between heaven
and earth, between life and death.
Demons are coming his way. Death is near.
His family line is cursed.
To deceive evil spirits,
he needs to get a new name.
A black chicken just laid an egg.
Bring it to me.
Now his name is Sabyr! Humble yourself
and accept your fate.
Now his name is Sabyr! Sabyr! Sabyr!
Let it be so. Amen.
That's how l became Sabyr,
which means ''Humble'',
as l found out later.
God just fulfilled my
grandfather's request
Ok, raise your hand up. Good boy.
Ezhi will check you, OK?
So you don't have any germs.
Oh, you've collected all
the lice from the train.
Don't be afraid. . . let me go,
let me go, good boy!
Mr. Kasym, l need man's help!
He is curcumsed.
Muslim, he is a Muslim.
A ''zhid'', that's what we call them
in Poland.
''Zhid''? Who is a ''zhid''?
A small Jew.
Look at you! A good Kazakh.
How cold.
Sashka gaining weight.
Grandpa Kasym, grandpa Kasym,
please give him to me.
Open your eyes, look at us. . .
don't be afraid, all people here are good. . .
Well, you are like new.
A real man.
He sees their black eyelashes.
And how humbly lice dies under
their tender fingers.
That is Ms. Vera, she is Madonna.
Madonna? Do you know who l am here?
l am Verka here, a shit. . .
And you are a good one,
Ezhik without a head or feet.
Without feet, Ms. Vera?
l bow down before you.
Ms. Vera, like your knight.
Don't bother, Ezhik, for God's sake
An orphan. . .
what an orphan. . .
Malfunctioning.
He needs to eat well,
and have chicken, butter and
sour cream when available.
Listen, why are his eyes are closed?
ls he blind, or what?
lt's a nervous breakdown.
His soul needs mercy, a big love,
my Madonna with a child.
Anyway, he will die.
What are you going to do with him, Kasym?
Maybe we should take him to the orphanage?
Sashke!
Here he is, our little Sabyrchik!
You, little bastard, don't you dare
be kidding with me. . .
Thoughts and looks of millions
are directed to Kremlin in Moscow.
Waves of soulful greetings
and warm wishes go to dear Stalin.
Ordinary people of the world glofiry him
as father and best friend,
who dedicated his life in effort
for freedom and happiness of workers.
Soviet people repeat words
of Zhambul with honor:
lf Stalin with us-the truth with us.
lf Stalin with us-we are stronger,
lf Stalin with us-the flag of powerful,
happy and sunny country flutters with us.
All meetings and conventions were
holding with a big enthusiasm.
Metal-makers, miners, machinists,
textile men, oil workers
Mama. . .
Vera. . .
Hey. . . Stop! Who is it? Let me go.
Come here.
Who are you? Whose are you?
An orphan? Where did he come from?
He's mine. My nephew.
He came for the school break.
Lying!
l know everything about you. . .
People like you don't have relatives.
Show me the documents.
Don't touch the boy, Balgabai!
Who then l can touch? You?
At least me.
You Verka. . .
l am Verka, thousand years Verka,
didn't you know?
So, you are not afraid of me at all?
Everyone is afraid of Balgabai.
Ezhik! Get the bottle!
Let's celebrate Sashka.
Ok, Balgabai?
Dombrovski?
What, polishman, you wanna run?
Yes, yes, Mrs. Policeman.
Run, run. . . You go five kilometers
you get five years. . .
You go twenty - you get twenty.
l can run a thousand kilometers.
You'll get shot in the neck!
Buy the turtle, sir, buy the turtle,
20 kopeks.
Why do we need a turtle?
Hey, kids, come here!
What are you selling?
Turtle, turtle. Buy turtle!
Again conserves. . .
Enough.
What are you doing?
Don't touch her!
l don't want your broth.
Drink! Hey, you will be sick!
No.
You can die. . .
Hey, look. l found ten kopeks!
Hey, what are you doing?
O, money!
Gleb, see what l found?
A whole pack!
Show me. Give me one!
Watch your ass!
Hi, Sultan. l've not seen you for a while.
Look what my guys found!
Sabyr!
Sashka. . .
Verka!
l'll get hiccups. . .
You aren't going to marry me. . .
Where is Sashka? Do you have him?
Yes, he has been here
and Balgabai came too,
was interested in him.
l had to call him my nephew.
So what is it?
You were told to get him
into the orphanage.
ln the endless steppes, where there are
no marks except the railroad,
a road from horizon to horizon,
leading into the unknown,
a sky for a runaway is open
and he does not have horizons.
Nevertheless, his sadness is deep
and there is no joy from this freedom.
Then he soaked in the smell
of steppes' heat.
This smell like a bur, stuck to clothes,
lives in the heart of
everyone who has been to the Kazakh
steppe at least once.
Sashka. . .
Hey, Sashka.
Hey, what are you doing
on our territory, ha?
We are the boss here!
l'll poke your eyes out. . .
Don't come up to me!
Hey, boys! Don't touch the boy.
Run, run, guys.
Come on, run.
Cannot kill animals.
Who?
Chicken!
Yes, you can.
No, you cannot!
Sashka, it's OK, you can.
Don't you feel sorry for them?
Why?
l love them.
They love me and we are fine.
l just don't understand!
You have a big mess in your head.
ln Moscow, we don't kill anybody!
A bright moon in a windless night,
Shining in the water.
A soul of a village is so deep,
Like a roaring lake.
Hey, Sashka!
Ms. Verka! Sashka!
ls he found?
Yes, he is.
Thank goodness.
Nomads. . .
Kasym grandpa! Are you alive?
Why you are not sleeping. . .
Almighty. Almighty. Allah!
A bright moon in a windless night,
what's next, grandpa?
Next: a light is blinking on the water...
At no windy night moonlight
is blinking on the water.
Wait! Get out!
Hold it.
Grandpa Kasym. . . you must be
stronger than God?
No, son. l am not stronger than God.
Yes, my grandpa also said you should
not be stronger than God.
Come on.
Did you get on?
While we were on the road, he talked to
me about God all the time
Quietly-quietly. Because you cannot
talk about him out loud.
He is terrifying. You know, grandpa Kasym,
l don't believe in him completely,
just a bit. . .
But my mother and father
did not believe in him at all.
Grandpa said that is
why they were arrested. . .
Yes..
All workers of Kazakhstan celebrate the
significant day of birth of great leader,
friend and teacher Stalin
with formidable enthusiasm.
Every day hundred of visitors
come over to the exhibition dedicated
to 70th anniversary of dear Stalin.
The exhibition is open at
Central Public Library of the Republic.
Young generation discover Stalin's
heroic effort
for revolution and nation happiness
by intent learning
and researching photos,
pictures and books of him.
Senior lieutenant Medynskyi arrived to
perform a special task.
So, we are going to shoot a movie?
Yes, sir!
For us, out of all arts,
movies are the most important.
Does everyone have a pass to
the secret location?
Yes, sir, everyone has one.
l warn you, the situation is like in
a war before the attack.
We understand, sir.
A big government affair.
Do you have cold water?
We don't have water to drink.
We will pay. We have the money.
Don't you understand Russian?
Hello, Asembala!
Asembala, let's play hide-and-seek, ha?
All right!
Let's go!
One, two, three, four, five, six,
seven, eight, nine, ten. . . .
Hey! Don't be afraid, boy,
we are not going to hit you.
l am not afraid!
You are from the level. . .
We don't hurt those.
Let's go with us.
Go, go! Move your feet.
Balgabai has a motorcycle between the feet.
Do you remember in trunk. . .
Come on, come on, l am getting cold.
Thank you very much, l don't smoke!
My name is Gleb! Shit, when l was born,
they wrote that name down.
But l am Pack.
Where are your parents? Are they here?
On the north.
They let them go soon. . .
And they will take me back.
Yes, they are here.
We all are here.
Will you join our gang?
Yes, l will. What do l need to do?
l need to get some money for surgery. . .
Bones break all the time.
The polish guy says. . .
calciumsh-shmalcioum is not enough!?
Hey, limping Timur!
Don't interrupt!
The polish guy says
there is a doctor in Almaty.
Freedman his name, he treats bones.
But it takes lots of money. . .
Hey, whitie, put more fire.
You say, money.
Hey. . . l think l know!
Yes! Water! Hot water!
Hey, guys, what's up with him?
We'll earn lots of money.
Come on, who needs more?!
Get me more.
l came up with it, pour for me.
l already poured for you.
ls the hot water ready?
Ready. Come on, pour,
don't burn your fingers.
Pour quickly, the train is coming.
Quickly, the train is coming.
Guys! Train! Train is coming!
Come on, guys, follow me!
Hot water. Spring water.
Buy water. Three kopeks. Hot water.
Hot water! Cold water! Buy water!
Hot water! Cold water, hot water.
Buy water! Don't be stingy!
Hot water! Buy water.
Hot water , buy hot water!
Hot water! Sir, buy hot water for
three kopeks. Hot water for three kopeks.
Sashka had a great idea.
How much did we make?
Let's count now.
Hey, you. . . What?
Come on, gang, all the money!
Here you go!
O-o, not little.
This is for Sashka, for his idea.
Thank you very much.
You need lots of money.
Leave it for yourself.
Can this fool to break through
the compartment?
May be she can, that is why she is a fool.
ls Sashka here?
Where did you take my kettle, silly boy?
Verka! Shit!!!
l will get you on your naked bottom!
What did you say?!
Come on, come on!!!
Hooligans.
You lost the lid, what am l going to do?
Why did you get together with this gang?
They are really homeless, orphans. . .
You, Sashka, remember,
you have nothing to do with them.
lf l see you with them again, you will
get a spanking, do you understand?
Kasym, ...what a person you have!
A gold one!
Our train is rushing ahead.
We have a stop, we have no other way.
We have a gun in our hands.
Wait. We are here.
Greetings to Balgabai, in-charge!
Again, he did Verka. What a miliziaman!
Verka is like a quick ambulance!
Hey, stop it, Verka is good!
What did l say? Did l say she is bad?
Go, work.
Hey, Kazakh, hey, Kasym.
What's up with you? What happened?
Ok, get up. Let's go.
Come one. Sit down. Come on.
What, polish guy, did you swallow your
tongue? Say something. We need to work!
So, what, Ezhik? ls it bad?
l cannot tell what it is. . . he needs to be
checked in a hospital. . .
until then,
he should not ride horses.
And he shouldn't be smoking.
All right, Kazakh,
l am going to treat you myself.
Dungan medicine is the best in the world!
Get up, let's go!
Kasym has changed since this day.
And what has changed
in you Sabyr the Humble?
What are you looking for at this market,
made of shattered pieces
of millions of lives.
Answer, who are you in the
land of your God
if a part of your soul was left out there
in the village of the migrants
and deported? lsn't all the land God's?
We got you!
Gleb, Gleb.
l have newspaper for you.
l have cigar paper.
Hey, it's my turn.
Give me your hand.
One, two, three. . .
Let me do it. Do it then.
Hey, what are you doing?!
School children of the
whole Soviet country
A gift for Stalin. . .
are making gifts to the anniversary
of our leader. . . Stalin.
The best gift can be given to
him personally by the winner.
lnteresting.
What if l make the gift?
Maybe he will let my parents go?
Wow! Where did you come from?
See, how white. He came himself.
How cute. . . White.
Will he be mine?
Whose is it? Whose are you?
Whose flock are you from?
May be it is for the good.
For the good. Here you go, it's yours.
Thank you, grandpa.
Play.
So warm.
Cute.
Hot water! Buy hot water!
Listen, may be l should call you
Keepeetok (i.e. hot water). Keepeetok!
Do you know how it is beautiful in Moscow?
She is not bad, is she?
Comrad Major, she is from special settlers.
Bring her in here.
Go, policeman, go, l am not holding you.
Where from?
Akmolinsk camp for wives of traitors,
58, Vera lvanova, sir.
ALGlR. . . a good camp. . .
l am not asking about it.
Where are you from?
Now it does not matter.
Strip off.
What is it?
A religious object?
Mine.
Take it off.
No, l won't.
No, my girlfriend put it on
me before dying, l never take it off.
Take it off.
No, l will not
l tell you take it off
l will not!
Neither steeps nor animals knew
what an unbelievable and terrifying
sacrifice had been prepared here.
Hey, Kazak, move.
God the Mother. Forgive me a sinner.
Forgive me, Lord! Forgive, Lord!
l am a sinner, a sinner l am.
Forgive me, oh, God.
Hey, boy, move away from the bottle!
A bolo.
You blind, you missed it.
Shut up!So, l am saying that Sultan
is not afraid of anybody,
even prisoners.
And he is not afraid of Balgabai.
Sashke! Show up your abilities!
l hate Balgabai, also.
For Verka's sake l hate him.
Hey, boys, the policeman is coming!
Verka!
Verka! Balgabai is here.
Verka! Open the door!
Open the door, you fucker,
or l'll take your puppy to police station
Verka, fucker, open the door.
Ok, we will see. Fuck!
Hey, what are you doing?
What are you doing?
Go away!
Take your uniform off.
Take it off, come out one on one!
You puppy, go away! What's up?
Take your uniform off!
Take it off, come out one on one!
You puppy!
Take your uniform off!
Take it off, come out one on one!
You puppy!
Come on boys, quick.
Are you up? Go, go.
Hey, you there, quiet.
Quick, quick.
lt can go through. Go, go.
So little but heavy.
Are you stuck? Go through.
Be careful.
Go, go! All right.
Wow! Take it.
Wow, so much food!
Sashke, are you asleep?
Sashke, where are you?
Hey, stop.
Guys!!! Jiggers!
Let's take off, boys.
Hey, you gang, stop. l'll shot.
l said stay. Where are you going? Stay.
Sashke!
Your name and your last name?
lt means your name is a thief and l will
send you to the prison, do you understand?
My name is Sabyr.
Sabyr?
May my eyes get poked,
if you are Sabyr! Sabyr!
That is true, ask Kasym.
Which Kasym?
One-eyed rail track man.
Track man. . .
Don't cry! Eat the apple.
Thanks, l hate them!
You hate them! Stop crying now.
We'll go and see who is going to
defend you this time!
Understand?! Go! Go ahead.
Let's go.
Thank you very much!
Hey! Lift up your eyes. Look here.
Listen to me: when you are leaving,
tell me where you are going and why.
Do you understand?
Yes.
You put me to shame.
Keepyatok, do you want more?
You had enough.
We are the same.
You got left alone and l lost my parents.
lt's OK, l will find them one day.
Catch him. Throw higher.
Give the money.
Take care of it.
Yes, sir.
Here you go.
Where are you?
Here, Comrade Major!
Quick, quick, quick.
Please, Comrad Major.
Kasym Batyrbaev, railroad man, local. . .
A war participant. . .
Animal.
Babi, do you sell animals?
We need all kind of animals. . .
Ha!? Deaf, are you?
He is contused.
We are no confiscating, we are paying.
For a big government thing.
A gift for Comrad Stalin's anniversary.
Comrade Major, he is absolutely lonely. . .
in our words..
Horsy- morsey! Are you a police, ha?
Are you a part of the family?
l know, you are all relatives. . .
And you relative,
are you selling an animal?
A Turtle, like a lemon!
Whose is this Abraham?
Perfect looking Kazakh!
Where did you get him?
l gave a birth to him!
You? From whom?
l wish l knew. . .
May be there from Balgabai, ha!
All right. . . A brave woman. . .
Good for her.
Let's go!
Wait! Wait!
Stop!
Take him for free. . .
Just make sure let Comrade Stalin know
that it is from me, Sabyr Povzner!
Let's go!
Let him my parents go free. . .
Grandpa Kasym. . .
lf we knew if Comrade Stalin
would like my gift or not. . .
Yes.
When l was like you Sashka. . .
l walked long ways. . .
to a far winter place.
l remember. . .throughout the steeps. . .
we put yurts. . .
big celebration. . .
Wedding! Thousands guess, can you imagine?
Lots of food, many games. . .
Our tribe was the most respected.
Many horses, camels. . .
Catching a girl! lt's a game. You have to
catch a girl. . . l caught up with one. . .
and kissed her.
And then?
A wedding then! We had three children!
Then hunger, . . . no one stayed alive.
And then?
A war came then.
And then what?
And then l had you.
Oh, Allah. . .
Listen,
l am alone and you are alone. . .
We are both alone here forever. . .
Let's, how do you say it. . .
well, live together, ha?
Like a husband and a wife. . .
Would you feel.
See, you cannot find like this anywhere!
Wow, a shell!
We have one like this in Moscow.
lt says ''gagry'' on it.
Mom and Dad brought it from the Black Sea.
Was a sea here before, too?
Everything was here before.
Once it seems there was a sea here.
Here you go, son.
Put it over there.
Lay it down over there.
Oh, God Almighty, give rest to
the innocent souls
and may the land be like a feather
for them. Amen.
Here you go.
A grandpa is here. . .
Who is your God, Grandpa Kasym?
God is one for everyone.
For me and for you.
For Ezhi, for mom Vera,
for Faty, for Gleb also?
One for all. . . for all, son.
What language does he speak?
He knows all languages,
the main thing is that the word
would come from the heart.
Remember this spot, this land,
someday you will return here, son.
Why, are you going to send me somewhere?
Hey, Kazakhs, move.
There is one more good news.
Hey, you're thieves.
Go, go from here.
Hey, how fat! lt would make good
''beshparmak'', enough for everyone.
You have no fault, we have no food.
The Almighty prepared you for us to eat.
Amen.
No, don't pick.
Soooo. You have not eaten without me,
have you?
What a good place.
Now you will be a healthy Kazak.
Add more salt, the meat would be softer.
Hey, be careful!
Why are you closing?
Hurrah! Bride and a groom!
l bless you!!!
Hey, Faty!
This is a gift for you from the Koreans
and Dungans of our region.
Thank you.
Sir, would you bless it?
Good for you! Thanks!
Finally, ''beshparmak'' is here!
Thank you, dear. All the blessings to you.
Dear guests, before a big feast
receive my blessings.
Let the people have peace
and let the country have order.
Happiness for the young. Amen.
Amen!
Here . . . the ears.
Somebody will be lucky now!
lt's for our Sashka so he can hear well.
The eyes are for the polishman
so he can keep an eye on Verka.
The neck - for Verka,
so you can turn around your Ezhi.
This is for my friend Faty,
so he can well. . . .
Speak, speak...
No! Chat!
Thanks!
And now friends, let's take this toast
for the bride and the groom.
Congratulation! Congratulation!
A bright moon in a windless night,
A light is blinking.
A soul of a village is so deep,
Like a roaring lake.
Verka, shit. . .
Dombrovskiy, get up!
l said get up!
Sit.
What's the party is here!
Verka, fuck you. . .
Verka. . .
Boys, run, a pistol. Run, quick.
Verka, look at me!
Handy Hoh, legs apart,
we are going to you!
Sir, don't, stop it, we are relatives,
don't shame me in front of people.
What, what happened, what did l do?!
Son of the bitch, you are an animal,
what relatives?
You are putting me to shame
in front of the people.
What are you doing, Kasym?
You are going crazy.
You ashamed me in front of everyone,
crooked old man.
l'll show you! l considered you as
a relative. You messed up my authority.
Get up! Everyone in your compartments!
Dombrovskjuy, shit!
How did you dare to raise you hand? Shit.
You raised your hand on the
Soviet authority, have you?
This is for you, Mr. Dombrovskuy
from Balgabai.
Let him go!!! Go away!
Let me go!!!
Ezhik!
Dear, what have you done?!
You killed the policeman!
Verka,. . .
l just. . . .
What?
Sir, l am not guilty, you saw, he himself. . .
Son of the bitch. . .
Ezhik!
Come on, don't die! Ezhik!
lt's not me, he himself. . .
l knew it will finish like this.
Curse you!
Get lost.
Do not leave me, please! Do not leave me!
Dear. . . lt's not me, he himself. . .
Open your eyes, dear, please.
Ezhik!
Lord! Then take me too!
This is food for you.
This is a picture of your parents.
This is the address of your relatives.
Do you understand?
Yes.
This is your grandfather's prayer book.
Hey, are you scared?
Remember, never be afraid of anything.
Take care of yourself, grandpa Kasym.
That's it. Let's go.
How will you be without me?
l don't want to leave.
Don't cry, son! Don't cry!
You are a man.
l don't wanna leave, grandpa.
Be happy, my son. Have a good trip.
Have a good trip, son.
Get up, get up!
Be happy, son!
Kasym grandpa. Take care of yourself.
l will come back.
Have a good trip, my son.
O, Almighty, if there is any fault,
forgive me.
Give me faith, and happiness to my Sashka.
Guys, we are attacked!
Let me go!
A police car came in the morning into the
village and arrested all the gang.
They were suspected in organized order
of the policeman.
Who shot Balgabai?
Sultan? Gleb? Or somebody else?
l could have been with them too
if it was not for the old Kazakh man,
whom God enthrusted me to once.
Many years later l found out that on August
29, 1 949, 1 70 kilometers from Semey,
an atomic explosion took place for
the first time in the USSR.
An anniversary gift for Stalin. . .
A competition for the best children's
gift to our beloved
Joseph Vissarionovich Stalin is taking
place all over our vast USSR homeland.
And now Asembala Koibagarova will
sing a folk song by Abai,
who is by the way from our land.
A bright moon in a windless night,
A light is blinking.
A soul of a village is so deep,
Like a roaring lake.
This is the tree and there is nothing
around it. Only these bits of fabric.
You can count how many people have been
under its branches.
How many days l have waited to be here
again to humbly accept
the past as the only and invaluable
and happy life given to me by the fate.
Here, among other lives the souls
of my grandfather,
Kasym, of repenting Vera,
her husband polishman Ezhi,
and restless Faty have found rest.
May they rest in peace. . .
l came back to call Kasym my father
and devote to him the prayer which
is read in memory of parents.
May His great name be blessed
forever and evere!
May the name of the Holy One be blessed,
uplifted, magnified and praised,
His name is blessed above all blessings
and praise,
and of all worship and comfort named
in the world!
Let us say Amen!